# 大家好 你看這個小黑 它下崽了哦
Hi everyone! Have a look at Blacky here. She has just given birth.
# 你看 全是黑的
Look! All are black.
# 四條黑狗
Four black puppies
# 不知道還有沒有
I wonder if there are any more.
# 去搞一隻雞給它吃
Let me make a chicken for her,
# 搞一隻老母雞來
make an old hen for her.
# 先把這個雞腎
First I slice the guts,
# 切一下
into pieces.
# 這是它的心
This is its heart.
# 就這樣切開
Cut it open.
# 雞頭
The chicken head,
# 這個雞頭也要哦 這個雞頭
I'm gonna take the chicken head as well, the chicken head.
# 等下煮熟了給小黑吃
I'll give it to Blacky after cooking it.
# 小黑現在不能吃生的東西
Blacky shouldn't eat any raw food at this moment.
# 就這樣煮熟
Just cook it.
# 雞腿
Chicken leg
# 你看 這兩條小狗
Look! These two doggies
# 拍點薑
I put some smashed ginger,
# 去去腥
to get rid of the bloody odour.
# 好啦 這些一起把它放下去 燉
Alright! I'm gonna put all these into the wok, and stew it!
# 先把雞腿放下去 這兩個大雞腿
The chicken legs first, the two big chicken legs
# 然後再一起下鍋
And then followed by everything
# 再加上這香菇 跟那個花生米
Together with the shiitake mushrooms, and also the peanuts.
# 哇 一大鍋
Wa! A whole big wok!
# 你看 這個肯定很香
Look! It certainly smells good!
# 就這樣慢慢燉 燉個兩個小時
So I leave it stewing. It may take a while. Stew it for two hours.
# 甚麼味都出來啦
All flavour will be released then.
# 你看 這個
Look at her!
# 這個母狗也快生了哦 這個母狗 應該是這幾天會生
This girl is also giving birth very soon. This girl, I think she's gonna give birth in the next few days.
# 你看這個
Look at her!
# 這個是 所有的狗的 狗的狗奶奶
She is the doggy grandma of, of all dogs, all dogs here.
# 這個那麼大的肚子 肯定又要生啦
Her belly is that big now. I'm sure she's also giving birth very soon.
# 大家猜 能不能猜的出來
Take a guess! Can you guess?
# 猜中了就送一個小狗給你們
Those who can guess correctly can have a free puppy.
# 不知道多少個 應該 五六個
How many? I think, five or six,
# 肯定有的 哦 有沒有
at least. Oh, am I right?
# 吃的那麼好
I feed you so well.
# 很高產的
You must be very productive.
# 胎胎都四五隻以上
She has at least four of five in every litter,
# 小黑只生了四隻
while Blacky has only four.
# 很聽話的這個狗
She's a very good girl.
# 現在好胖啊現在你看
She's becoming chubby now, look!
# 一身都是肥肉
Her whole body is covered with fat.
# 等它帶了 帶完崽的話就可能瘦很多
After, after her puppies have weaned, she might be much more slender.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt,
# 不要那麼多鹽
but not too much.
# 看看熟了沒有 哎呀
Let's see if it's alright. Aya!
# 精華
The essence!
# 太燙啦
It's too hot!
# 嗯
Um!
# 爛啦 剛剛好
Soft and mushy! Perfect!
# 嘗個雞 這個雞翅
Let me try a chicken, this chicken wing.
# 啊~好燙
Ah~ So hot!
# 剛剛好哦 你看這個 花生米
It's perfect! Look at the, the peanuts!
# 花生米好吃
Peanuts are tasty.
# 這個香菇也是
And the mushrooms too
# 我們吃的差不多啦就給小黑吃
I'll give it to Blacky when we have enough.
# 哇 這個大雞腿
Wa! This big chicken leg
# 全部都爛啦 你看 一搗就碎掉 這個 雞腿肉
It's all soft and mushy now. I can easily smash it with the chopsticks, I mean the meat on the chicken leg.
# 鹽味剛剛好
The amount of salt is just right.
# 一點也不鹹
It's not salty at all.
# 再嘗個香菇
Let me try the mushroom as well.
# 香菇還是很好錯誒
The mushrooms are in fact really not bad.
# 這個 我先吃 吃的差不多了再拿來 餵那個小黑
Well, I feed myself first. I'll feed, feed Blacky when I've had enough.
# 你看這個花生米 這個花生米就生吃
Have a look at the peanuts! The peanuts are mine.
# 嗯 好香啊
Um! It smells so good!
# 這個雞爪
Let me take a chicken foot.
# 好燙
Hot!
# 你看 這還有一點 撈一點飯 搞點飯就給那個
Look! Here's still a little bit. I'm gonna mix it with some rice, with some rice, and then give it to, you know,
# 小黑吃 雞頭 雞肉 是不是
to Blacky. Chicken head, chicken meat, right?
# 把這個倒下去
I pour it here.
# 你看 小黑餓急啦 來
Look! Blacky is starving. C'mon!
# 嘗下這個 好不好吃
Try it! Does it taste good?
# 先吃 少吃一點 剛生完
First, don't eat too much. You have just given birth.
# 這一條跑到這屁股這[SIC]邊啦 (註︰他應該說「後邊」)
One has gone to the back of her butt here.
# 哎呀 這條小黑狗
Aya! A black puppy
# 到前面來 前面才有奶喝的
Go to the front! There's milk only in the front.
# 嗯 香菇它都吃掉啦 可以哦
Um? She eats the mushrooms as well. Not bad!
# 看 好喜歡吃
Look! She likes it very much.
# 它舌頭
Its tongue,
# 一直在吃 想吃奶啦
it's craving, craving for milk.
# 這條狗 鑽到那前面去幹嘛
This puppy, what is it doing in the front?
# 應該是跟
I think its colour is like,
# 跟它媽媽一樣的頻色 有點黃 有點黑
like its mom's, a bit brown and a bit black.
# 是不是
Right?
# 四個聚在一起就很暖和
It's warm when all four of them are clinging together.
# 現在小黑好會帶崽咯現在
Blacky takes very good care of her babies now.
# 你看 現在小黑吃的多歡啊 嘖
Look! Blacky is eating so merrily now.
# 差不多一瓢它都吃完啦
She has almost finished the whole ladle.
# 好好帶崽哦
Take good care of your babies, got it?
# 嗯 這一條 這一條看一下
Um? This one, this one. Let me have a look.
# 這一條是母的
This is a girl.
# 跟小黑一樣的 看到沒有 這裡有點黃
She's like Blacky. See? A bit brown here
# 小黑很聽話的
Blacky is a very good girl.
# 吃
Go on!
# 吃飽喝足了
She's eaten enough.
# 吃奶吃奶吃奶
Milk, milk, milk here
# 是不是 把腳放過來
Is that alright? Put your leg here.
# 這樣子放 這樣子躺下來
Put it here, and then lie down.
# 是不是
See?
# 這樣子躺下 全部小狗都吃的到奶
Lie down here, then every puppy can have a share of milk.
# 嗯 好好帶崽啊
Um! Take good care of your babies.
# 這個就放在這裡
I'll leave the ladle here.
# 又有湯 又有湯又有肉
There's soup, there's soup, and meat.
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 讓它慢慢地成長 經常搞點好吃的給它吃
Let them grow day by day. I'll gonna give them good food very often.